A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, History of the University, Addresses, Announcements and News Articles FA905
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, History of the University, Addresses, Announcements and News Articles
1901-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA905
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
The work of The Institute concentrated on basic research. The hope was that the discoveries might, in the long run, be applied to the public welfare, but the basic purpose was to provide an environment for exploratory original research by individuals under no compulsion to produce immediately useful results.
Scientific work of The Institute was first carried on through grants-in-aid made to researchers in scattered laboratories. This program decreased as the Institute's own laboratories developed. July 1, 1904 temporary quarters were rented at 127 East 50th Street, New York and work began there about Nov. 1, 1904. Those recruited for the first staff were Eugene L. Opie, Samuel J. Meltzer, Hideyo Noguchi and Joshua Edwin Sweet. Added to the staff very shortly were Phoebus Aaron Theodor Levene and John Auer. Alexis Carrel joined The Institute in 1906 and Jacques Loeb in 1910. On June 13, 1907 the Board of Directors voted to establish various classes of association with The Institute. The classes were: Member (for an indefinite period); Associate Member (for five year periods; amended in 1911 Rules to "a term of years); Associate of The Institute; Fellow of The Institute; Scholar of The Institute (which was dropped in the Rules amended 1928). The first Members of The Institute were Simon Flexner, S.J. Meltzer, E.L. Opie, and P.A.T. Levene.
In April 1906 the Central Laboratory with animal house and power house, located on York Avenue and 66th Street were ready for use. Simon Flexner, the first Director of the laboratories had been unanimously elected Director of The Institute on Oct. 25, 1902. However, not until a meeting on Jan. 17, 1920 did the Board make clear its sense that these were two offices, both held by Simon Flexner. The Office of Director of The Institute was clearly added in amended Rules Oct. 18, 1924. Simon Flexner was Director of The Institute and Director of the laboratories until his retirement in 1935. He was succeeded in both offices by Herbert S. Gasser, 1935-1953.
In 1910, at the York Avenue site a Hospital was opened so that the investigations of the Laboratories could be supplemented by the study of certain diseases as they actually occur in man. The Rules for the Scientific Directors as adopted on Jan. 21, 1911, provided that The Institute be comprised of two coordinate departments, Laboratories and Hospital. Rufus Cole was the first Director of the Department of the Hospital and continued in this post until his retirement in 1937 when he was succeeded by Thomas M. Rivers. The Hospital accepted only a limited number of patients, limited further to classes of diseases under study in the Hospital laboratories. The By-Laws of the Corporation provided that The Institute make no charge to persons treated at the Hospital for professional care rendered or for board and lodging. Classes of appointment to the Hospital were Physician, Assistant Physician, Resident Physician, Superintendent and Assistant Superintendent. In 1946 an amendment to the Rules provided that the titles be as follows: Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital; Physician to the Hospital; Assistant Physician to the Hospital; Resident Associate Physician; Senior Assistant Physician; Superintendent of the Hospital; Assistant Superintendent of the Hospital.
In 1914, at a location about three miles from Princeton, N.J. with Theobald Smith as Director, a new Department of Animal Pathology was established. In June 1915 the Rules were amended to make this coordinate with the Departments of Laboratories and Hospital. When Theobald Smith retired in 1930 Carl TenBroeck became Director of the Department which in 1931 was expanded by the appointment of Louis O. Kunkel who headed the new division of plant pathology into the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology.
The Director of each Department was appointed by the Board of Scientific Directors, and the Director of The Institute by the Corporation. In the different departments separate laboratories were organized under the guidance of a Member or Associate Member. The broad divisions of scientific fields varied from time to time in accordance with scientific developments and the interests of the Members, but always with consultation, approval and direction of the Board of Scientific Directors.
In 1953, after the retirement of Herbert S. Gasser, an extensive reorganization was undertaken. Thomas M. Rivers, who served for two years as Vice-President of the Corporation and at the same time, Director of the Laboratories, Director of the Department of the Hospital and Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital retired in 1955. The position of Director of The Institute was abolished and also the organization into departments.
On and after November 19, 1954 when the Charter of the Corporation was amended so that the Corporation became part of the University of the State of New York The Institute had the power to confer degrees. On June 27, 1958 by amendment to the Charter the corporate name was changed to The Rockefeller Institute and on May 27, 1965 the Charter of The Institute was amended in its entirety and the name changed to The Rockefeller University.
The University is organized into laboratories, each headed by one or two senior scientists rather than into categorical departments. The scientific work of the laboratories is under the direction of the President.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 401
Arrangement
Chronological.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Addresses, announcements, news articles and reprints.
Medical research; Medical education; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Life sciences; Operations management; Biology -- Research; Medical sciences; Greene, Jerome D.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller Foundation
- Addresses, announcements, news, articles, reprints, 1901-1975
  - Photographs of temporary quarters: 127 East 50th Street (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Addresses delivered at laboratory opening, 1906 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Nicolle, Maurice. "Institut Rockefeller" Extraits de La Presse Medicale, no. 26, 1907 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Auer, John. "The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research" Reprint from Medical Record, (Imperfect), 1909 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report on the RIMR with special reference to a permanent endowment, 1910 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Greene, J.D. Needs of additional space, 1912 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Greene, J.D. Estimated additional cost of maintenance due to erection of new wing, 1912 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rockefeller, J.D. Jr., Welch, William; Simon Flexner. Addresses at 20th Anniversary of RIMR. Cosmopolitan Club, 1922 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Levinthal, Walter. "Das Rockefeller Institut in New York: Methodik und Ergebnisse der Erforschung filtrierbarer Virusarten nach persönlichen Eindrucken" Sonderdruck aus Medizinische Klinik 1925 Nr. 38/39 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes translation by A.v.d.O.
  - "The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research" Medical Journal and Record, 1928 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "RIMR, Hospital, Department of Animal Pathology" Sonderdruck Forschungsinstitute, ihre Geschichte Organisation und Ziele hrsg. von Ludolph Brauer, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Addresses at 20th anniversary of opening of RIMR Hospital, 1938 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Parkhurst, G. "War everywhere" Good Housekeeping, 1937 August (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York City as a Medical Center; historical retrospect. Reprint from Annals of Internal Medicine v. 11. no, 1938 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Castiglioni, A. "Panorama della medicina americana. Minerva medica an. 25, v. 11, no. 46. With translation, 1934 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - News release of J.D. Rockefeller, Jr. retirement, 1950 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Weidner, E. "When John D. listened" Coronet, 1952 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chase, Merrill. 3 graphs showing RIMR growth, 1901-1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brimble, L.J.F. The Rockefeller Institute, NY "A new graduate university" Nature v. 183 pp. 1629-1634, 1959 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Walsh, J. Rockefeller University: science in a different key Science, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Medical Litterateur" MD Medical Magazine, pp. 191-198, 1972 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Yunker, Barbara "On the Nobel Farm" New York Post, 1972 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper articles 8pp. on Milbrook (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Nobel Factory that flourishes in Manhattan" reprint from Fortune, April 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "An Anniversary Album" booklet of historical photographs prepared by The Rockefeller University in honor of the 75th Anniversary (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller University reprint from "Dictionary of American History" revised ed. 1976, 1976 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes Publishers Weekly notice of publication, 4pp.
  - Bylinsky, Gene. "Medicine's last word in 'think tanks'" Medical Economics 4pp. 104-114, 1976 October (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Freese, Arthur S. The Wizards of York Avenue, NRTA Journal, pp. 9-12, 1976 November-December (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Storm van Leeuwen, Willem. Indrukken van een studiereis naar America. Personer, nieuwe onderzoekingen medische laboratoria en klinieken, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Dedicated to Simon Flexner. 97 pages on RIMR and staff. Published 1920, der Haag.
  - Fruton, Joseph S. Book review: The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, an essay review. (George W. Corner. A History of The Rockefeller Institute, 1901-1953) Journal of the history of medicine and applied sciences, 21 (1966) 71-77 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Walsh, John. "The Rockefeller University: No time for philosophers" Science, 195 (1977) 272-275 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cole, Thomas A. Newspaper article: Rockefellers aid early research in South Bend Tribune, 1977 September 18 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anderson, Alexandra. "Neighborhood Avenue, 1978 October 27-30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Physiologist Vol. 26 No. 2 April 1983, with article by Herbert Chasis, "History of collaboration by Department of Physiology at New York University School of Medicine" pp. 64=70, 1983 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unpublished manuscript with a section on RIMR & its Hospital. Given to RU Archives by Dr. Hess (Box 2, Folder 7)